American Historical Financial Documents Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
American Historical Financial Documents Collection
1734-1874
1777-1790
GEN MSS 1081
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.76
(6 boxes)
Correspondence, accounts, receipts, checks, printed currency, circular letters, printed forms filled out in manuscript, and other printed material related to American finance, currency and lotteries during and after the Revolutionary War. Series I, Currency and Public Debt Documents, includes letters by Jacques-Pierre Brissot de Warville; Albert Gallatin; John Gibson; Alexander Hamilton; Gouverneur Morris; Robert Morris, and Thomas Willing. There is a small group of letters between Gouverneur Morris and the London bankers Sir Francis Baring, Edmund Boehm, and Thomas Henchman concerning their possible investment in the "new American funds" in 1790 and 1791. Printed material includes Thomas Paine's Decline and Fall of the English System of Finance (Philadelphia, 1796) as well as circular letters and debt payment tables. Other contents include reports on Revolutionary War loans and other contemporary financial matters; receipts issued by several states, particularly Connecticut and Massachusetts, between 1780 and 1789; and samples of state and Continental Congress paper money. Series II, United States Lottery Documents, contains letters by state agents for the Continental Lottery; accounts and account logs for the lottery; memoranda; and a printed lottery ticket from 1779.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, accounts, receipts, checks, printed currency, circular letters, printed forms filled out in manuscript, and other printed material related to American finance, currency and lotteries during and after the Revolutionary War. Series I, Currency and Public Debt Documents, includes letters by Jacques-Pierre Brissot de Warville; Albert Gallatin; John Gibson; Alexander Hamilton; Gouverneur Morris; Robert Morris, and Thomas Willing. There is a small group of letters between Gouverneur Morris and the London bankers Sir Francis Baring, Edmund Boehm, and Thomas Henchman concerning their possible investment in the "new American funds" in 1790 and 1791. Printed material includes Thomas Paine's Decline and Fall of the English System of Finance (Philadelphia, 1796) as well as circular letters and debt payment tables. Other contents include reports on Revolutionary War loans and other contemporary financial matters; receipts issued by several states, particularly Connecticut and Massachusetts, between 1780 and 1789; and samples of state and Continental Congress paper money. Series II, United States Lottery Documents, contains letters by state agents for the Continental Lottery; accounts and account logs for the lottery; memoranda; and a printed lottery ticket from 1779.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Co. on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund and the Library Associates Fund, 2003.
Arrangement
Organized into two series, both arranged in the order in which the material was received. Series I., Currency and Public Debt Documents, contains examples of currency and printed forms issued by various states and the Continental Congress, followed by alphabetically arranged correspondence, circular letters, official documents and printed ephemera. Series II, United States Lottery Documents, contains roughly chronologically arranged correspondence and other papers.
Debts, Public -- Law and legislation -- United States; Debts, Public -- United States; Debts, Public -- United States -- States; Finance, Public -- United States; Finance, Public -- United States -- States; Lotteries -- United States; Paper money -- United States; United States -- Politics and government -- 1783-1789; United States -- Politics and government -- 1789-1797; United States -- Politics and government -- 1797-1801; United States -- Politics and government -- 1801-1815; Accounts -- United States -- 18th century; Checks (bank checks) -- United States -- 18th century; Continental currency -- United States -- 18th century; Paper money -- United States -- 18th century; Baring, Francis, Sir, 1740-1810; Boehm, Edmund; Brissot de Warville, J.-P. (Jacques-Pierre), 1754-1793; Gallatin, Albert, 1761-1849; Gibson, John, 1729-1782; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804; Henchman, Thomas; Morris, Gouverneur, 1752-1816; Morris, Robert, 1734-1806; Reed, Joseph, 1741-1785; Willing, Thomas, 1731-1821; United States. Board of Treasury; United States. Congress; United States. Continental Congress; United States. Department of the Treasury
- Currency and Public Debt Documents, 1774-1874; Series I
  - State of Connecticut: Treasury certificate. Hartford, Connecticut, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - State of Connecticut: Treasury certificate. [Hartford, Connecticut], 1781 February 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - State of Connecticut: Treasury certificate. [Hartford, Connecticut], 1782 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - State of Connecticut: Treasury certificate. [Hartford, Connecticut], 1782 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - State of Connecticut: Treasury certificate. [Hartford, Connecticut], 1782 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - State of Connecticut: Treasury certificate. [Hartford, Connecticut], 1789 February 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Continental and state currency: 15 samples of Continental Congress currency and state emissions. Various places, including Philadelphia, New London, Newcastle, Annapolis, etc., circa 1774-1780 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - State of Massachusetts Bay: Committee of War certificate. [Boston, Massachusetts], 1777 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - State of Massachusetts Bay: Committee of War certificate. [Boston, Massachusetts], 1778 July 29 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - State of Massachusetts Bay: Treasury certificate. [Boston, Massachusetts], 1778 February 28 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - State of Massachusetts Bay: Treasury certificate. [Boston, Massachusetts], 1779 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - State of Massachusetts Bay: Treasury certificate. [Boston, Massachusetts], 1780 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Commonwealth of Massachusetts: To the Honorable Henry Gardner, Esq., Treasurer and Receiver-General of the said Commonwealth. Boston, Massachusetts, 1780 November 25 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 111)
  - Commonwealth of Massachusetts: Treasury certificate. [Boston, Massachusetts], 1782 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Commonwealth of Massachusetts: Treasury certificate. [Boston, Massachusetts], 1783 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Commonwealth of Massachusetts: partially printed form, completed in manuscript, acknowledging receipt of interest on a loan to the Massachusetts Treasury by Nathaniel Appleton, 1789 January 9 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - State of Pennsylvania (Morris, Robert): three blank checks. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, circa 1780 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - State of Rhode Island and Providence Plantations: printed loan receipt, completed in manuscript, for the interest payment received on a loan to the state of Rhode Island by Joseph Clarke. Newport, Rhode Island, 1785 November 26 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - State of South Carolina: printed form, completed in manuscript, crediting the tax account of the estate of James Lingard [Charleston, South Carolina], 1774 March 24 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Beckley, John: manuscript copy of an extract from the journals of Congress regarding the public creditors of Pennsylvania, 1789 September 28 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Beckley, John: manuscript notice regarding the public debts of the states and outstanding loan certificates, 1789 September 21 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Blaine, Ephraim: manuscript circular letter, signed, requesting the total sum owed to merchant John Ladd Howell by the Commissary General's Office. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1782 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Brissot de Warville, Jaques Pierre: three manuscript documents concerning Brissot de Warville's activities in America on behalf of a French mutual fund and tontine. Paris, France, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Carey, H. C.: Currency Inflation: How it has Been Produced, and How it May Profitably Be Reduced: Letters to the Honorable B. H. Bristow, Secretary of the Treasury. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Continental Congress: Resolution authorizing commissioners to endorse Massachusetts state currency, 1780 June 29 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Continental Congress: Resolutions recommended to states for the restoration of public credit, 1783 March 18 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 112)
  - Continental Currency: manuscript summary of a legal case regarding a failure to pay a debt drawn in continental currency, 1778 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 108)
  - Continental Currency: manuscript notes settling an order for Continental money taken in 1778. Preston Connecticut, 1785 November 19 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Continental Currency: scale of depreciation. Haverhill, Pennsylvania, 1799 September 12 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Dallas, Alexander J.: manuscript notice concerning acceptable forms of currency, 1815 August 15 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - De Berdt, Dearman, and Co.: An Account of the Nature and Prices of American Stocks. London, England, circa 1790 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Gallatin, Albert: letter from the Secretary of the Treasury transmitting a statement of claims. Washington, D. C., circa 1810 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Gibson, John: autograph letter, signed, from John Gibson, Auditor General, to Nathaniel Appleton. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1777 June 23 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Gibson, John: autograph letter, signed, from John Gibson, Auditor General, to Nathaniel Appleton. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1778 August 21 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Gibson, John: autograph letter, signed, from John Gibson, Auditor General, to Nathaniel Appleton. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1779 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Goodhue, Benjamin: autograph letter, signed, from Benjamin Goodhue, Congressman from Massachusetts, to John Templeton, regarding additional federal assumption of state debts. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1792 November 15 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Hamilton, Alexander; Huntington, Samuel: two letters concerning data collection for Alexander Hamilton's report on public credit, 1789 September 26 and November 9 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Hamilton, Alexander: autograph letter, signed, from Alexander Hamilton, Secretary of the Treasury, to an unidentified recipient, 1790 October 13 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Hamilton, Alexander: autograph letter, signed, from Alexander Hamilton, Secretary of the Treasury, to an unidentified recipient, 1791 January 14 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Hamilton, Alexander: The Report of the Secretary of the Treasury, (Alexander Hamilton), on the Subject of a National Bank, Read in the House of Representatives, 1790 December 13. New York, New York, 1811 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Hamilton, James: autograph letter, signed, from James Hamilton, Financier of Texas, to Leslie Combs, Presidents of the Lexington Danville Railroad, regarding the public debt of Texas. Washington, D. C., 1854 July 11 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Hancock, John: manuscript copy of an unsigned letter to an unidentified recipient, regarding the deplorable financial condition of the United States. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1780 March 7 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Hickcox, John H.: A History of the Bills of Credit or Paper Money Issued by New York, from 1709 to 1789. Albany, New York, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Hopkinson, Francis: list of currency bills being issued, 1778-1782 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Huntington, Samuel: circular letter, signed, from Samuel Huntington, President of the Continental Congress, to the several states. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1780 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Huntington, Samuel: letter, signed, from Samuel Huntington, President of the Continental Congress, to Joseph Reed. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1780 June 29 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 109)
  - Irvine, William: autograph letter, signed, to John Nicholson. New York, New York, 1790 February 4 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Jenifer, Daniel, of St. Thomas: autograph letter, signed, to the treasurer of the western shore, on the subject of Continental money. [Annapolis, Maryland], 1785 July 11 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Lee, Arthur; Osgood, Samuel; Livingston, Walter: autograph letter, signed, to William Ellery, regarding receipt of loan interest and the consequences of paper money, 1786 August 8 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - State of Massachusetts Bay: printed Revolutionary Loan Certificate, completed in manuscript and signed by Massachusetts Treasurer Henry Gardner. [Boston, Massachusetts], 1777 September 26 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - State of Massachusetts Bay: An Act to Prevent Monopoly and Oppression. Hadley, Massachusetts, 1777 February 24 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Province of Massachusetts Bay: Treasury certificate. [Boston, Massachusetts], 1775 June 26 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Morris, Gouverneur; Morris, Robert: 20 autograph letters regarding Gouverneur Morris's representation of Robert Morris's affairs in Europe. Various places., 1790-1792 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes correspondence between Gouverneur Morris and the London banking partnership of Boehm, Baring and Henchman (Edmund Boehm, Sir Francis Baring, and Thomas Henchman) on a proposed investment in the "new American funds"
  - Morris, Robert: autograph letter, signed, to Richard Varick, George Washington's Recording Secretary, regarding credit notes for military supplies. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1782 June 3 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Morris, Robert: manuscript account book of Robert Morris, personally managed by Thomas Willing, first President of the Bank of North America., 1782-1786 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Morris, Robert: manuscript copy of a letter to Elias Boudinot, President of the Continental Congress, on the need to suppress Congressional expenditures. [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania], 1783 July 28 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Morris, Robert: engraved stock certificate for three shares of the North American Land Company, signed by Robert Morris. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1795 March 16 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 114)
  - Osgood, Samuel; Livingston, Walter: autograph letter, signed, to Nathaniel Gilman, Commissioner of the Continental Loan Office for New Hampshire., 1788 November 11 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Paine, Thomas: The Decline and Fall of the English System of Finance. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1796 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - State of Pennsylvania: To the Citizens of Pennsylvania., 1779 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 110)
  - State of Pennsylvania: The Philadelphia Price Current., 1784 November 29 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Reed, Joseph: autograph letter, signed, from Joseph Reed, former President of the Supreme Executive Council, to William Bell, Philadelphia merchant, regarding American finances. London, England, 1784 March 11 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Revolutionary War Debt: Table for the Payment of Principal and Interest of Loans, Agreeable to the Resolutions of Congress of the Twenty-Eighth Day of June, 1780. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1783 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Revolutionary War Debt: A Plan of a Tontine to Consist of 1000 Shares of 100 [pounds] Each, to Be Divided into Seven Classes..., circa 1789 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Revolutionary War Debt: circular letter addressed by the Secretary of the Treasury to the American stockholders residing in Great Britain and Ireland. London, England, 1807 August 24 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Revolutionary War Finance: four letters between Michael Hillegas, first Treasurer of the United States, and Nathaniel Appleton, Continental Loan Officer for Massachusetts. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, and Boston, Massachusetts., 1780 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Revolutionary War Finance: Table for the Payment of the Second Year's Interest Due on All Sums Loaned to the United States between 1778 February 28 and 1780 February 28. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Revolutionary War Finance: signed letter from Arthur Lee, Samuel Osgood, and Walter Livingston, to Thomas Smith, regarding counterfeit certificates., 1787 February 12 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Revolutionary War Finance: The Registered Debt of the United States, circa 1790 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Revolutionary War Finance: An Act, Supplementary to the Act Intituled "An Act Making Provision for the Redemption of the Whole of the Public Debt of the United States.", 1807 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Smith, William: Price current for Hydestown, New York., 1785 July 16 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Treasury Department: Report of the Committee, Appointed...to Examine the Accounts of the United States, Relating to the Public Debt., 1800 May 8 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 113)
  - Trumbull, John: partially printed loan certificate, completed in manuscript, regarding interest on a loan. Connecticut, 1782 August 9 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Webster, Pelatiah: To the Stock Holders of the Bank of North America, on the Subject of New and Old Banks. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1791 May 28 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Willing, Thomas: autograph letter, signed, from Thomas Willing, President of the Bank of North America, to Thomas Mifflin, Governor of Pennsylvania., 1791 March 12 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Manuscript invoice of goods account of Robert Livingston, 1734-1735 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - American Revolution: To the Inhabitants of the United States of America... Letter from John Jay, President of the Continental Congress. Hartford, Connecticut, 1779 May 26 (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 115)
- United States Lottery Documents, 1777-1781; Series II
  - Continental Lottery: Autograph letter, signed, from Jonathan Purviance, Maryland agent for the Continental Lottery, to the managers of the lottery in Philadelphia. Baltimore, Maryland., 1777 March 8 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Continental Lottery: Autograph letter, signed, from Nicolaus Houer, Continental Lottery agent, to Jacob Barteh, a Philadelphia merchant, regarding available tickets to be sold., 1777 July 29 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Continental Lottery: List of Continental Lottery tickets sold, with prices. [Winchester, Virginia?], 1777 July 24 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Continental Lottery: Autograph letter, signed, from a lottery ticket agent, to Jacob Barge, returning unsold tickets. Lancaster, Pennsylvania., 1777 August 8 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 116)
  - Continental Lottery: Autograph letter, signed, from Alexander Donaldson, agent of the Continental Lottery at Yorktown, to the managers of the lottery. Yorktown, Virginia., 1778 December 28 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Continental Lottery: Autograph letter, signed, from George Bryant, agent of the Continental Lottery for Pennsylvania, to the managers of the lottery in Yorktown. Lancaster, Pennsylvania., 1778 May 5 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Continental Lottery: Autograph letter, signed, from Jacob Broom, later signer of the U.S. Constitution, to the managers of the United States Lottery Office. Wilmington, Delaware., 1778 December 27 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Continental Lottery: Autograph letter, signed, from John Hartman, agent for the Continental Lottery in Reading, Pennsylvania, to an unnamed recipient. Reading, Pennsylvania., 1778 December 2 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Continental Lottery: Autograph letter, signed, from John Pierce, Jr., agent of the Continental Lottery for New York, to the managers of the lottery in Philadelphia. Albany, New York., 1778 April 27 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Continental Lottery: Autograph letter, signed, from Matthew Irwin to the managers of the Continental Lottery in Philadelphia, regarding his account. Yorktown, Virginia., 1778 May 9 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Continental Lottery: Autograph letter, signed, from Robert Traill, agent of the Continental Lottery for Pennsylvania, to John Mease and Joseph Bullock, managers of the lottery, regarding unsold tickets. Easton, [Pennsylvania], 1778 December 27 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Continental Lottery: List of Revolutionary War Lottery Tickets sold, with prices. [Winchester, Virginia?], 1778 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Continental Lottery: Williams, Jonathan. Manuscript extract of a letter relating to the sale of lottery tickets in Boston, in an unidentified hand. [Boston, Massachusetts], 1778 January 24 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Continental Lottery: United States Lottery Class the Second, list of tickets sold by Robert Traill. Easton, [Pennsylvania], 1778 December 27 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Continental Lottery: Autograph letter, signed, by Titus Hosmer to the managers of the Continental Lottery. [Middletown, Connecticut], 1779 October 11 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Continental Lottery: Autograph letter, signed, from Samuel Kennedy to John Ord regarding collection of money due from the sale of Continental Lottery tickets in the form of Government emissions., circa 1779 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Continental Lottery: Manuscript account log of the Continental Lottery recording reimbursement amounts for several Continental Lottery agents. [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania?], 1779 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Continental Lottery: Manuscript account log of the Continental Lottery recording reimbursement amounts for several Continental Lottery agents. [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania?], circa 1779 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Continental Lottery: Manuscript calculations relating to the Continental Lottery. [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania?], circa 1779 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Continental Lottery: Hillegas, Michael. Memo relating to Michael Hillegas's account. [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania?], circa 1779 (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Continental Lottery: Printed lottery ticket, class the third, with manuscript signature., circa 1779 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Continental Lottery: Account of lottery money received in the loan office. Boston, Massachusetts., 1780 July 12 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Continental Lottery: Account of money received by Nicholas Gilman, commissioner of the loan office in New Hampshire, from the agent of the United States Lottery, for the sale of lottery tickets. [Concord, New Hampshire?], 1780 July 29 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Continental Lottery: Autograph letter, signed, from John Hartman, Pennsylvania agent of the Continental Lottery, to Sharp Delany and Joseph Bullock, managers of the lottery in Philadelphia. Reading, Pennsylvania., 1780 December 16 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Continental Lottery: Autograph letter, signed, from Thomas Harwood, Continental loan officer for Maryland, to Sharpe Delany and Joseph Bullock, managers of the Continental Lottery. Annapolis, Maryland., 1780 July 7 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Continental Lottery: Autograph letter, signed, from Wensley Hobby, Continental Lottery winner, to the commissioners, seeking his prize. Middletown, Connecticut., 1780 November 20 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Continental Lottery: Autograph letter, signed, from Wensley Hobby, executor of the estate of a Connecticut lottery agent, to the managers of the Continental Lottery. Middletown, Connecticut., 1780 September 25 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Continental Lottery: Autograph letter, signed, from Wensley Hobby, executor of the estate of a Connecticut lottery agent, to the managers of the Continental Lottery in Philadelphia. Middletown, Connecticut., 1780 August 14 (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Continental Lottery: Autograph letter, signed, from William Houston, delegate to the Continental Congress from New Jersey, to the managers of the Continental Lottery., 1780 March 16 (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Continental Lottery: List of Continental Lottery agents to whom no credit was given via the sale of third class lottery tickets. [Philadelphia, Pennsylvania?], circa 1780 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - Continental Lottery: Manuscript computations regarding the Continental Lottery., circa 1780 July (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - Continental Lottery: Manuscript list and receipt for funds received from a Continental Lottery agent., circa 1780 (Box 3, Folder 100)